Finding Aid for the The Salynn McCollum Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
The Salynn McCollum Papers
bulk 1960s
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0699
3.35 linear_feet
Biographical Sketch
Mary Salynn McCollum was born in Tulsa, Oklahoma. Her parents were Walter C. and Hilda McCollum. Both of her parents were from Tennessee, with her father coming from the Waverly area and her mother coming from Memphis. She spent time in New York before attending college in Tennessee. In 1958, she began her first year of college at the George Peabody College for Teachers in Nashville, Tennessee. Her course of study focused on instruction for intellectually and developmentally disabled children.
During her junior year in college, Ms. McCollum became involved in the Nashville Non-Violent Movement, the Nashville branch of the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). In February 1961, she attended a Nashville Student Movement meeting as a guest of Central Committee member Lester Carr. No committee members knew who she was, but they assumed she was a reporter because she took notes throughout the meeting. Ultimately, she became the first secretary of the Central Committee. She was also one of the ten college students who participated in the first Freedom Ride from Nashville to Birmingham, Alabama on May 17, 1961.
Salynn McCollum was an active participant in the Civil Rights Movement between 1961 and 1965. Despite pressure from her family and Peabody College to cease her involvement, she continued to work with SNCC following the Freedom Ride. She wrote the “I am a Freedom Rider” series depicting her experiences on the Freedom Ride and her subsequent jailing at the Birmingham Jail. She worked as a SNCC field secretary in different locations in the South. She was particularly active in Nashville, Tennessee; Cairo, Illinois; Charleston, Missouri; and Des Moines, Iowa.
As both a northerner in the South and a white woman in the Civil Rights Movement, family, friends, and acquaintances struggled to understand why she chose to participate in the Nashville Non-Violent Movement. For Ms. McCollum, her desire to live her life according to her convictions and religious beliefs pushed her to work tirelessly for equality.
Following her time with SNCC, Salynn McCollum returned to her interest in instructing children. She worked as a Head Start teacher and later a director. When possible, she still speaks to groups about her experiences as a Freedom Rider.
Scope and Content Note
The Salynn McCollum Papers consist of 2.085 linear feet of materials. The collection includes correspondence and writings by McCollum, as well as newspaper clippings, journal and magazine articles, and photographs. The majority of the material represents McCollum’s participation with the Civil Rights Movement during the first half of the 1960s. Many items were generated while she was a field secretary for the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC).
The collection is organized into two series: Personal Material, which includes Salynn’s correspondence, poetry, and journal entries; and Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee Material, which includes many of that organization’s publications, as well as field notes, committee meeting minutes, committee promotional materials, and many newspaper articles involving SNCC activities Salynn was involved in.
- Series I: Personal Material
  - Correspondence – Outgoing (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence – Incoming, May 3, 1961 – June 26, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence – Incoming, August 1, 1961 – September 27, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence – Incoming, October 10, 1961 – December 17, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence – Incoming, January 9, 1963 – November 14, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence – Incoming, January 13, 1964 – June 26, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence – Incoming, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Articles (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Publications – Newsletters, Articles, Resources (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Writings – Articles (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Writings – Coursework (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Writings – Journal (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Writings – Notes (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Writings – Poetry (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Writings – Poetry (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Writings – Stories (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Writings – Thoughts (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Writings – Thoughts (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series II: Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee Material
  - Administrative Documents (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Documents (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bibliographies, Catalogs, 1 1961 – 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Civil Rights Organizations Publications – Southern Regional Council (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Civil Rights Organizations Publications – Southern Regional Council (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Civil Rights Organizations Publications – U.S. National Student Association (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence – Incoming, April 27, 1962 – May 14, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence – Outgoing, July 25, 1962 – July 1, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Flyers & Programs (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Histories (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Journal Articles (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Laws (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Memoranda & Letters (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Handouts, Prints, Posters (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Nashville Non-Violent Movement Documents (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Nashville Non-Violent Movement – Coordinating Committee Minutes, March 1961 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Nashville Non-Violent Movement – Coordinating Committee Minutes, April 1, 1961 – April 12, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Nashville Non-Violent Movement – Coordinating Committee Minutes, April 13, 1961 – April 29, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Nashville Non-Violent Movement – Coordinating Committee Minutes, May 1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - News Releases –, 1961 – November 6, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - News Releases –, January 1963 – July 1963 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - News Releases –, September 4, 1963 – 1964 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Newsletters –, March 1961 – June 5, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Newsletters – The Student Voice, Summer 1962 –, February 18, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Newsletters – The Student Voice, February 25, 1964 – August 5, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Other Organizations Publications –, August 1957 – September 1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Other Organizations Publications –, April 1962 – August 1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Other Organizations Publications –, September 1962 – June 29, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Other Organizations Publications –, September 1964 – June 7, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Other Organizations Publications –, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets & Booklets (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Promotional Materials (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Promotional Materials (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Reports –, May 19, 1962 – August 8, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Reports –, August 16, 1962 – October 1, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Reports –, October 1, 1962 – February 18, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Reports (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Songs & Music Information (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Writings – Notes, Drafts (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Writings – Notes, Drafts (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Writings – Notes, Drafts (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Writings – Notes, Drafts (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Writings – Notes, Drafts (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Writings – Notes, Drafts (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Writings – Notes, Drafts (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Writings – Reflections and Accounts (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Writings – Reflections and Accounts (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Writings – Speeches (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Writings – Speeches (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Writings – Speeches (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Articles –, September 23, 1961 – July 3, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Articles –, July 5, 1962 – July 16, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Articles –, July 16, 1962 – July 24, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Articles –, July 24, 1962 – August 15, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Articles –, August 16, 1962 – October 4, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Articles –, 1962 – April 7, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Articles –, April 17, 1963 – November 19, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Articles –, November 25, 1963 – April 29, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Articles –, May 17, 1964 – March 10, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Articles –, March 12, 1965 – March 20, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Articles –, March 21, 1965 – March 31, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Articles –, March 31, 1965 – October 8, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper Articles –, February 6, 2006 – February 26, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper Articles –, Undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper Articles –, Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Newspapers – The Southern Patriot, April 1960 – May 1964 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Newspapers – The Empire Star Weekly, January 21, 1961 – May 27, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Newspapers – The Empire Star Weekly, August 19, 1961 – September 11, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Newspapers – The Empire Star Weekly, September 18, 1961 – January 6, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Newspapers – The Empire Star Weekly, January 12, 1962 – February 10, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Magazine Articles, April 25 1961 – December 17, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Magazine Articles, April 10 1962 – September 25, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Magazine Articles, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Magazines – The New Yorker, August 29, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Magazines – Motive, May 1960 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Magazines – Motive, October 1960 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Magazines – Motive, November 1960 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Magazines – Motive, December 1960 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Magazines – Motive, April 1961 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Magazines – Presbyterian Life, August 1, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Magazines – Harper’s Magazine, October 1961 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Magazines – U.S. News & World Report, March 26, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Magazines – Playboy, July 1962 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Magazines – The Progressive, June 1963 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Magazines – Liberation, June 1963 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Magazines – Liberation, Summer, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Magazines – Liberation, September 1963 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Magazines – U.S. News & World Report, September 9, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Magazines – Newsweek, October 21, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Magazines – The Progressive, February 1964 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Magazines – Parents’ Magazine, July 1964 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Magazines – Newsweek, July 13, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Magazines – Newsweek, August 3, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Magazines – Newsweek, November 20, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 24)